Let me show you version one of
instrumental components. It's my toolkit
that I've always wanted when building
out my apps with Ruby on Rails. So
whether I'm vibe coding in cursor or
hand coding, I'm usually doing a hybrid
of both. I find that building with my
components helps me ship highquality
products fast and pack in a lot of power
with just a few commands. So let me show
you how it works. So once you're inside,
you'll find uh documentation and
instructions on how to install
instrumental components. You have two
options here. You can install the gem,
which lets you install individual
components into your project on an as
needed basis, or you can use our starter
kit, which gives you a fresh Rails
application that comes with instrumental
components and all of the components
pre-installed for you. I'm going to walk
through the process of installing the
gem. So, if you haven't done it already,
you'll need to start up a new Rails
application. The only hard requirement
here is that we're using Tailwind
version 4 or up. So I'm going to Rails
new demo app. That's what we'll call it.
And we will add
Tailwind. Then you'll want to CD into
your project. From there you can pop in
our installer gem into your gem file.
and run bundle
install. Finally, you'll want to copy
this oneliner down here. This will
install our component generators and
register your license all in one shot.
We'll just run
that. Okay, so that was successful. Now,
you might see these red messages here.
That just means that your project
doesn't yet meet the base requirements
to run instrumental components. That is
we need active storage installed and
active and action text installed. Let's
get
those and we'll db migrate those. Let's
run bin dev and we should have our rail
screen up and running. Cool. Now,
typically the very first component that
I like to install is our simplest
component and that is just to install a
root page. Instead of the rail screen,
we just want a hello world page with a
controller and a view and put that into
our routes file. So, let's run rails g
instrumental root page. And that's how
all of the commands in instrumental
components work. Rails generate or rails
g instrumental colon the component
name. And with every generator, it's
going to start with an overview of
what's about to be installed into your
project. This is a super simple one, but
some of them are more complex, and
you'll see a long list of of tasks that
it's about to run. So, you'll just
approve that to proceed. I'll hit
return. And then you're going to watch
the terminal go step by step installing
these files into your project. And then
when it's done, you'll see a message
like this in green, which gives you an
overview of everything that just
happened. In this case, we've added two
files, a controller and a view. We've
added one line to our routes, and we are
all good to go. See what our site is
looking like. It's not going to be
exciting. It's just going to be a hello
world. Okay. So, we've got our first
component installed into our project.
All right. Now, let's really get our
project going. I'm going to install four
components that I always use on every
project. We want to start with
authentication, so login along with a
user signup flow. Then I'm going to
install the teams component, which sets
up accounts and users, an invitations
system for team members. Then I'm going
to install a back-end dashboard for me
and my team to manage users and accounts
in my product. And finally, I'll install
instrumental commerce. That's our Stripe
integration so that I can start charging
for this SAS product that I'm going to
build here. Now we'll start with
authentication. That's railsg
instrumental authentication. And
actually this is going to fail because
it's going to check requirements and
first it's going to tell me that we
actually need to install the core rails
authentication generator that came with
rails 8 and so our authentication layer
is built on top of that. So we want to
run rails g authentication. So this is
starting with the core rails
authentication which just gives us you
know like a login flow and we can
migrate. Okay. So now we'll be ready to
run the same command again. Rails g
instrumental
authentication and once again we have an
overview of the component that we're
about to install. Now most of these
components actually pull in multiple
components all in one shot. Right? So,
our authentication component also makes
use of all these other ones like the
logo component, the menus, drop downs,
buttons, tool tips, and a whole bunch of
stuff. So, it's going to give you a list
of everything that it's about to install
along with this. We want to proceed.
Now, part of this is it's going to
actually install a layout into our
application. And when we install a
layout, it asks whether we want to make
that our default application layout or
give it another name. In this case,
yeah, we'll use the application layout.
So, I'll approve that. Okay. Okay, so
now it's going to step through the
installations of, you know, 15 different
components and you can see it making
progress. Um, the blue lines kind of
give us like an update on which step in
the process that we're at. You'll see
these green lines which means that
another component has successfully been
added to the project. Now, by default,
this is happening in slow mode, right?
Where we can sort of watch it happen
step by step. You can just add the the
fast flag to make this go all in one
shot. And you can even add that to your
config file for instrumental uh so that
it uses fast mode every time. Okay, so
that's all set. When it's finished, it
gives us this recap which in this case
it shows 58 new files have been inserted
into our project. We can go through
those and review those later on. And it
also did some code insertions which
means it it took some some existing
files, it left its code intact and it
just added a bit of functionality and
methods and things um to those. In this
case, we did add a migration. So we'll
need to migrate that. And we also added
a gem. It pulled in our icons component
which uses the loose rails gem. Okay.
So, oh, and we added a few routes to our
to our routes file. Let's go ahead and
get this migrated. We want to run
bundle. Let's see how we're
doing. Okay. So, here is our new and
improved login flow and our
authentication flow. Actually also gave
us a sign up and registration flow.
Inside it gives us like user profiles
and avatars and time zones and a whole
bunch of other stuff. Um, but before I
actually sign up for an account, I want
to make sure that I set up my accounts
model and users and teams and the
association between those. And that's
where our teams component is going to
come in. So, I'm going to stop the
server and I'm going to run rails gin
instrumental teams. And this time I'm
going to use the fast command to make
sure that we just run through this much
faster. Now, we always start with our
overview. In this case, we're going to
install the teams component plus these
additional components. But it also found
that 11 other components that would be
used by the teams component are already
installed in our project. So we're not
going to install them again. All right,
let's proceed. Okay, so that was much
faster this time. Of course, here is the
recap of everything that was just
installed with the teams component. 40
more files have been inserted into our
project. We've got controllers, you
know, views, partials, couple code
insertions. Uh there are some new
migrations. Again, we set up the the
accounts model and the route and the
users and a whole invitation system. So,
we're going to migrate that and we added
the page gem that adds uh pageionation
and we have all the styling built in for
that as well. And we added a couple of
routes. All right. So, let's get this
stuff migrated. Bundle. Cool. I'm going
to start the server. I've got a shortcut
for
that. All right. So, I'm going to sign
up for my
account and I'm dropped into the
application. This is our application
layout and we have a few different
layouts that we can install with
instrumental components, but this is the
one that came with our uh our early
installations. Up here, I've I have a
user menu. I've got my account settings.
I've got my user profile settings,
password. Here is my team section. So, I
can actually uh send an invite to other
team members and give them another role.
The the mailers are all wired up for
that. So, they receive an email, they
accept the invite, then they have a flow
for them to come in. I can add
additional accounts and then I can even
have like an account switcher up here.
So all of that is now installed into my
project. Good to go. All right. The next
thing I want is an admin dashboard where
I can manage things on the back end like
users, accounts, and later on managing
products and things for my product. So
let's stop the server. I'm going to do
Rails G instrumental admin. Let's use
fast mode. Actually, you know what?
Instead of instead of manually adding
that every time, I'm going to go into my
config, go into instrumental YAML, and
these are the configuration options for
how your instrumental components work.
So the first thing is I'm going to turn
fast mode to true. So it just uses that
every single time. Now, while I'm here,
let me tell you about the prevent
overwrites list. you know, building with
components. What typically happens is
you'll install some components and then
you'll go into the components themselves
and customize them and actually adapt
them to your project. So, as we're
installing lots of components and
reinstalling and updating components,
you want to be sure that you're not
overwriting your customizations. So,
that's where the prevent overwrites list
comes in. You can just list out the
files in your project that you've made
some customizations to or that are
really important that you don't want to
overwrite and we will prevent the
overwrites. And if you ever need to grab
some of the updated code from the new
improved components that come out
throughout the year, you can always go
into our starter kit and find the PR and
and and grab the individual pieces of
code and import them into your project.
Okay, so let's go ahead and get our
admin component installed. I'm not going
to use the fast flag because that should
happen automatically. So here is the
overview. the admin component plus a
plus two new components will be
installed and it uses 12 other
components that we already have
including buttons, icons, breadcrumbs,
logo, toggle, and you know, a bunch of
other stuff. Okay, so we're going to
proceed and that's all done. So now we
have our recap. Bunch of files were
overwritten because they were not in our
skip overwrites list. That's okay. We
inserted some code into things like our
application controller and a couple
other places. And we did add a migration
and a couple of routes. We'll run the
migration. Now, in order to actually use
the admin panel that we've just
installed, I have to make my user an
admin. That's like, think of it like a
super admin in your application. That
happens directly in your database. So,
you could do that in Rails console or I
like to use table plus on Mac and I have
a shortcut to launch it. Um, and so I'm
going to go into my user record that I
had registered earlier and we're going
to change this admin flag to true. and
I'll restart the
server. Okay, so now that I've made
myself an admin, that gives me a special
link here. All right, so here I am in my
backend admin panel for my product. It
uses the secondary color, so it's a
little bit different from the main
application. So I know that I'm here in
the admin. Now, out of the box, we have,
you know, a main dashboard. We can add
stuff to this later. I've got my users
list and I've got my accounts list. I
can inspect any individual account. I
can see which users are in each account.
And this one happens to be myself. But
if I were viewing another user, we'd
have a button here and I can impersonate
that user. That's really helpful for
customer support. And as the app grows,
we can add more things to our admin
dashboard that we need to manage like
commerce, like our products and
purchases and orders and subscriptions
and customers. And that's actually what
we're going to install next. Let's get
into it. All right. I'm going to stop
the server. And now I'm going to install
instrumental commerce. That is our
Stripe integration. Let's get to it.
Rails G
instrumental
commerce. Okay, so this one is going to
install a couple of new components,
including our drag and drop reorder
component, our FAQ component, some copy
to clipboard stuff. All right, we're
going to proceed. That's all done. This
was a really big one. So, um, you know,
we've added 165 new files into our
project. Um, lots of stuff. you know,
there's like products and prices and
subscriptions and payment methods and
checkout flows and um you know, user
payment history and you know, all this
stuff is it's it's a it's a full
commerce system for selling
subscriptions and one-time product with
a pricing table and checkout flows and
everything. So, um a lot of stuff
happened. We have a bunch of migrations
to run. We added the Stripe gem and we
added the positioning gem along with a
bunch of routes. All right. So, let's
get the all migrated bundle. Okay. So,
let's see how we're doing here. Now,
again, I'm I'm viewing my admin panel.
If I refresh now, we've just added
commerce into our admin panel. So, here
in the commerce section is where I can
set up my products, my prices, plans.
Um, you know, I can also see purchase
activity, payments, subscriptions. Now,
I'm going to have a totally separate
video and a bunch of guides on commerce
because it really goes deep. I don't I
don't want to waste time here in this
demo, but you know, as we can see, it's
all here. Um, I'm going to go back to my
app. All right, one more thing before I
wrap up this demo. Let's actually start
building our product, like our features,
right? So, let's use the instrumental
scaffolding component to scaffold a
model and some views. I'm going to use
this app as like a place to list my
guitars, right? So, let's do this. I'm
going to stop the server. I'm going to
do rails gin instrumental
scaffold. And this works just like a
rail scaffold except it's a little bit
better. We're going to call this
guitars. Each one is going to have a
name, a
brand purchased. That'll be a
datetime. And how about
favorite? That's a boolean. All right,
let's run that once again. And here's
the overview. We're going to proceed.
It's going to ask us which column is
actually going to define the name. This,
you know, it's going to use that when it
sets up the controllers and things. We
also have the option to give each guitar
a unique slug like in the URL. And yes,
I want to do that. And we can actually
generate that from the name of the
guitar or generate a random one. We do
want to generate it from a field. We'll
choose the uh the name field. And uh
yes, we want to pageionate the index of
guitars. So I'm going to agree to that.
Okay, so um it just ran through the
whole process very fast. Here is the
recap. We installed some components and
it did add a migration for guitars.
Let's run that. Restart the server.
Let's go to guitars. Instead of needing
to update the URL directly, I want to
actually update my main navigation. I'm
going to
update global
nav. So this partial
handles handles the side navigation. And
you can see some sample code in here
which will actually give us like a a top
level and a suble navigation. I'm just
going to add a second one
here and that's going to link to guitars
path. We'll give it an
icon. See how we're doing. Okay. So
there is our guitars link. It takes us
into our guitar section. Cool. Let's add
a new guitar. All right. So here, you
know, it just gives you a form. Uh, very
simple. Show view um, edit. And now
we're back on an index. These are
totally customizable. We've got some
like settings drop downs here for each
one. We can delete one. Let's add
another one. Now, of course, everything
is mobile optimized. So, you can take a
look at that. We've got a mobile menu
all built in and everything is dark mode
friendly. So, all of that is all set for
you as well. Let's take a look at our
routes. You know, we've installed a
bunch of routes. It's nicely organized.
You can go in here and and organize it
however you want. Let's check out that
guitars controller. You know, it added a
whole bunch of controllers and billing
code and commerce code and admin panels
and name spaces and all that stuff is
just organized for you. It's all here.
You can check it out. We're using
Tailwind version 4. You can customize
all of your colors. So, if we look into
views under shared components, this is
where most of the components live. So,
for example, here's the drop-own
component, and all of this has been
meticulously built out to be fully
customizable. These are just basic Rails
ERB partials. You can pass a whole bunch
of options and attributes into them and
change them up um without uh without
changing the core component. But if you
need to, all of your component code is
right here in your project. You own it.
You're it's good to go.
We've got some layouts that we've
installed like the authentication
layout, the application layout, the
admin
layout. We built out an invitation
system and you can check out all these
things. We we follow um common patterns
across the project using a lot of Rails
conventions which makes it really easy
for you and your team to maintain and
also for LLMs like and and using tools
like cursor and wind surf when you're
vibe coding. It's all standard Rails
stuff. So uh you know it it makes it
really um easy to build out applications
really fast. So that's a look at
instrumental components. There are many
more components already included and I'm
releasing new ones all the time. So
check out
instrumental.dev. Thanks for watching.